# ANDRÉS SOLÍS MONTERO

Updated: October 7, 2015

www.solism.ca · ☎ (613) 265-4482 · ☑ andres@solism.ca
 803-173 Cooper St · Ottawa ON · Canada K2P0E9

#### **OVERVIEW**

**Research** Strong background in Computer Vision and Image Processing applied to shape analysis, scientist object detection and tracking applications.

**Developer**Over 10+ years of experience in software and web development. Particularly interested in Object Oriented Programming languages and scripting solutions. Developer who enjoys simplicity in design, creative code, and innovation. Experienced in C++, Java, Python and Web technologies.

**Teaching** Teaching Computer Science and Programming Languages for over 5+ years. Has taught experience over 10 courses.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant and PhD Candidate

University of Ottawa, Canada

Research on shape analysis, object detection and tracking solutions for augmented reality, robot localization, and surveillance applications. Design, develop, and validation of algorithmic solutions. Responsible for writing up research papers and presenting research findings.

Reference: Jochen Lang  $\cdot$  +1 (613) 562-5800 x 6317  $\cdot$  jlang@eecs.uottawa.ca Reference: Robert Laganière  $\cdot$  +1 (613) 562-5800 x 6707  $\cdot$  laganier@eecs.uottawa.ca

2011–2012 Senior Web Developer

Design, development, validation and deployment of the javascript template engine powering UniWeb. Create server-client web applications for the UniWeb product (PHP, HTML5, CSS3 and ¡Query).

Reference: Diego Macrini +1 (613) 828 6274 · macrini@proximify.ca

2010–2011 Senior Web Developer

Dalen Design Development and maintenance of e-commerce website: Hot Tub Covers Canada

(PHP, MySQL and jQuery).

Reference: Jessica Dalen +1 (613) 421 2686 · jessica@dalendesign.ca

2009–2010 Software Developer

Geomatics using high resolution imagery (Java, and C++).

International Inc.

Design and development of tools for the forest industry. Image analysis of forest stands using high resolution imagery (Java, and C++).

Reference: Frank Hegyi +1 (613) 526 9967 · fhegyi@hegyigeomatics.com

2008–2010 Research Assistant

University of Research on image processing techniques to extract relevant features from images.

Ottawa, Canada

Design develop and validation of algorithmic solutions. Responsible for writing up

Design, develop, and validation of algorithmic solutions. Responsible for writing up research papers and presenting research findings.

Reference: Amiya Nayak · +1 (613) 562 5800 x 2165 · anayak@eecs.uottawa.ca

Therefore. Timiya Nayak

2006–2008 **Software Developer**Navaera USA

LLC

2010-Present

**Proximity** 

Development of web and multi-platform tools for automatic clustering of documents from the web based on their content and metadata (Java, C#, and Python).

Reference: Matthew Adler · madler@navaera.com

2006-2008

**Network Administrator and Software Developer** 

University of Havana, Cuba

Design, development, and validation of network administration tools for user monitoring, domain login, email access, and internet quota management. Provide network support and IT services.

Reference: Sofia Sanjuán Gómez · +53 (7) 873 0123 · sanjuan@rect.uh.cu

#### **EDUCATION**

2010-Present

**Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science** GPA: 10.0/10.0

University of Ottawa, Canada

Thesis: Efficient Feature extraction for Shape Analysis, Object Detection and Tracking Robust feature representations to aid shape analysis, object detection and tracking.

Supervisors: Prof. Jochen Lang & Prof. Robert Laganière

2009-2010

Master of Computer Science GPA: 10.0/10.0

University of Ottawa, Canada

Thesis: Towards Feature Detection based on Morphology of Objects on Images Extracting lines and corners from images based on the morphology of objects.

Supervisor: Prof. Amiya Nayak

2001-2006

Bachelor of Computer Science GPA: 4.56/5.0 (magna cum laude)

University of Havana, Cuba Thesis: Diskless Cluster: Parallel and Distributed Systems

Bootable Cluster LiveCD based on Debian GNU/Linux distribution.

Supervisor: Prof. Joel de la Noval

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- 2015 Andrés Solís Montero, Jochen Lang, Robert Laganire. A General Framework for Fast 3D Object Detection and Localization Using an Uncalibrated Camera. IEEE Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV 2015), pages 884-891, Jan. 2015.
- 2012 Andrés Solís Montero, Hicham Sekkati, Jochen Lang, Robert Laganire, Jeremy James. Framework for Natural Landmark-based Robot Localization. Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Computer and Robot Vision (CRV), pages 131-138, April 2012.
- 2012 Andrés Solís Montero, Jochen Lang. Skeleton pruning by contour approximation and the integer medial axis transform. *Computers & Graphics*, 36(5), pages 477-487, March 2012.
- 2010 Milos Stojmenovic, Andres Solis Montero, Amiya Nayak. Colour and texture based pyramidal image segmentation. *IEEE International Conference on Audio Language and Image Processing (ICALIP)*, pages 778-786, Nov. 2010.
- 2010 Andres Solis Montero, Milos Stojmenovic, Amiya Nayak. Robust detection of corners and corner-line links in images. *IEEE 10th International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (CIT)*, pages 495-502, Jun. 2010.
- 2010 Milos Stojmenovic, Andres Solis Montero, Amiya Nayak. Co-parent selection for fast

region merging in pyramidal image segmentation. IEEE 2nd International Conference on Image Processing Theory Tools and Applications (IPTA), pages 243-248, July 2010.

Andres Solis Montero, Amiya Nayak, Milos Stojmenovic, Nejib Zaguia. Robust Line 2009 Extraction Based on Repeated Segment Directions on Image Contours. IEEE Symposium: Computational Intelligence for Security and Defence Applications (CISDA), pages 1-7, July 2009.

Milos Stojmenovic, Andres Solis Montero, Amiya Nayak. Link Shifting Based Pyramid 2009 Segmentation for Elongated Regions. Signal Processing, Image Processing and Pattern Recognition, Springer Berlin Heidelberg, pages 141-152, 2009.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2009 – 2015	Teaching	Assistant:

University of Ottawa

Operative Systems (CSI 3131), Summer 2015.

Introduction to Computing II (ITI 1121 - Java), Winter 2014

Introduction to Computing I (ITI 1120 - Java), Fall 2013.

Introduction to Computing I (ITI 1120 - Python), Fall 2015.

Advanced Programming Concepts in  $C++\{11\}$  (CSI 2372). Fall 20{10,12,14}.

Programming Paradigms. (CSI2120). Winter 20{11,15}.

Computing Concepts for Business (CSI1306 - Guest Lecturer). Fall 2009.

2006 - 2008

Havana

Network Administration in GNU/Linux, University of

Sept-Nov 20{7,8}

Relational Database Model Concepts,

Sept-Nov 2007

Object Oriented Programming with Java and C#,

April-June 200{7,8}.

Microsoft Office Tools (Word, Excel, Access),

April-June 2006

# SKILLS & EXPERTISE

Expertise

Computer Vision · Image Processing · Data Structure & Algorithms · Object-Oriented Programming · RDMS (i.e., MSQL, MySQL, Postgres, and SQLite) · Networking · Web Development/Design · e-Commerce · GIS · MVC

Markup and Programming Languages

 $C++\cdot C\cdot C\#\cdot Java\cdot PHP\cdot Python\cdot Matlab\cdot JavaScript\cdot Prolog\cdot Perl\cdot Bash\cdot Prolog\cdot Perl\cdot Perl\cdot Bash\cdot Prolog\cdot Perl\cdot Bash\cdot Prolog\cdot Perl\cdot Bash\cdot Prolog\cdot Perl\cdot Per$ JavaScript · Haskel · HTML 5 · XML · CSS 3

Software Development Tools

OpenCV · Eclipse · Visual Studio · Xcode · Git · SVN · make · ¡Query · LATEX · Adobe Photoshop · Adobe Illustrator · Adobe Dreamweaver · OpenOffice · Microsoft Office Tools

# HONORS & AWARDS

NSERC Engage Grant Program with Thales Canada. 2015

NSERC Engage Grant Program with You.i labs. 2014

2012 NSERC Engage Grant Program with Cohort Systems Inc.

- 2011 NSERC CRD Grant with Pulse Microsystems Ltd.
- 2010 International Admission Scholarship from University of Ottawa.
- 2010 Ontario Centres of Excellence Grant with Hegyi Geomatics International Inc. Project: Green Earth (GIS).
- 2009 Excellence Scholarship from University of Ottawa.
- 2009 Ontario Centres of Excellence Grant with Hegyi Geomatics International Inc. Project: Green Earth (GIS).
- 2009 MITACS Accelerate Internship Program for graduate and postdoctoral fellows. Project: Advanced Tools for Forest Inventory and Management.
- 2006 Magma cum laude graduate as Bachelor in Computer Science
- 2004 Creator of "linUHx" GNU/Linux distribution adopted by three Cuban Universities: University of Havana, CUJAE, and UCI.
- 2004 2nd position at 10th International Convention "Informática 2004, Cuba." Project: Electronic Magazine "E-zines".

### TECHNICAL REVIEWS - JOURNALS AND CONFERENCES

IEEE Transactions on Image Processing. TIP 2015.

IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo. ICME 2013.

IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation. ICRA 2013.

IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo. ICME 2012.

IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo. ICME 2011.

7th IEEE International Conference on Mobile Ad-hoc and Sensor Systems. MASS 2010.

## ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Languages ENGLISH: Full professional proficiency

**SPANISH**: Mothertongue

Affiliations ACM member · IEEE member · International High IQ Society member

Interests & Motorcycle Riding · Dancing · Music · Soccer · Volleyball · Skating

**Hobbies**